

4383 Eldoret 30100 KE Available for travel/relocation +254703475446 <u>leekiplimoarusei@gmail.com</u> DOB: 27/11/1991 Gender: Male www.linkedin.com/in/lee-arusei-b09033a0/

□ Researcher □ Statistician

Great Interactions with data and commendable observations skills and make things work Best

Business Experience ■ Startups & Large, Multinational Corporations ■ Mastermind for Business Growth Public & Private Sector

Background – Valuable Regulatory Skill Set

Highly trained leader and expertise with skills and Experiences not limited to being Data analysis /Economics, and Monitoring & Evaluation, Research Projects with broad range of professional experience not less than 4 years . Decision making skills within Statistical Research, Economic models in the field and industry has made Businesses add value and hence exponential growth has been evident. Managerial skills with wide range of experience both onsite and offshore of professional field.

EDUCATION HIGHLIGHTS

Duration	Institution	Achievement
Aug. 2012 to Dec. 2016	MASINDE MULIRO UNIVERSITY OF SCIENCE AND TECHNOLOGY	Bachelor of Science Mathematics in Statistics
Feb 2008 to Nov. 2011	UASIN GISHU HIGH SCHOOL	Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education.
1998-2007	SINONIN PRIMARY SCHOOL	Kenya Certificate of Secondary Education (KCPE).

Executive Highlights

- ➤ **Professionalism:** Competence, judgment, diligence, self-respect, and worthiness of the respect of humanity.
- > Structural skills: Ability to collaborate with professional teams of other organizations, seek improvement of research services and to offer new and different options to solve problems/ meet client needs.
- > Strong analytical skills: Ability to analyze complex situations; theoretical, analytical, and evaluative the skills helps to identify issues, formulate opinions and make conclusions and provide solution.
- ➤ Creativity: Ability to actively seek improvement of statistical services and to offer new and different options to meet community need. Can conceptualize innovative ideas for the improvement of the research department and building partnership with other institutions.
- ➤ Client Orientation: Ability to establish and maintain productive partnerships with clients by gaining their trust and respect, identify client's needs and match them to appropriate solutions, and anticipate problems.
- > Statistical skills: Knowledgeable on emerging technologies in Data analysis;
- **Research skills:** collection, capture, cleaning and analysis of both primary and secondary data.
- ➤ Communication skills: excellent drafting skills and demonstrated ability to write projects, reports and compiling training manuals and this can be demonstrated well using computer programs.
- > Technical skills: Ability to capture, classify, index, organize, data and share knowledge.

Computer Skills

Windows 2010/2008/2003/2000 Advanced Server, Windows NT/95/98/2000/XP/7, All versions of Microsoft Office (MS Word/ Excel/PowerPoint/ Microsoft Access), MS Project Ultra Edit Text Editor, SPSS, Fund Master, R, MATLAB, LATEX, Tableau, Microsoft Visual Studio 2010/2008/2005, C++, C#, Visual Basic 6.0

EXPERIENCE HIGHLIGHTS

The Eldoret National Polytechnic-Town Campus

Feb 2021-to date

Currently **I am able to train the students with the skills** that will aid them in both social and economic developments apart from normal class lessons. The passion for teaching and mentoring students is very evident in such a way that the students enjoy my presence in the classrooms.

Delivering the curriculum content as outlined in the syllabus.

I have been able to impact knowledge of mathematics, Statistics, ICT as postulated in the technical college's curriculum school calendar to individual students; my greatest achievements is that I have been able to make tremendous progress in the syllabus and my students always understand the concepts. Evaluating the academic and social growth of students by administering CATs and assignments. During the call for papers in the June International conference at the Eldoret National Polytechnic; Under the theme "Competencies in Research, Science and Innovation for Sustainable Development (CIRIS2021), I manage to write a paper under a sub theme Education and Training for sustainable development and the title of my Work is Tourism, Hospitality and Leisure in a Post-Pandemic World. The Paper shall be soon published

Actively participated in the Inter-departmental sports activities. I was nominated to co-ordinate the town campus team and I was therefore congratulated overwhelmingly for the **best coordination** and active engagement in making the sports day a success.

I am very resourceful when it comes to ICT related problem issues. **Able to assist the coordinator and the deputy in making the best** Timetable and examination analysis for the Town Campus.

I was appointed and deployed to Invigilate KNEC Examinations July Series whereby **I was always assigned the large groups** for I did managed and presented the best results.

State Department for Industrialization Public Service Internship Program

Oct 2019-Oct 2020

Engaged with;	Achievement	
2030 Water Resources I was able to stress the urge in harmonizing of data , Main Objective is to unify all the		
Group	agencies and develop data in all requirements pertaining to water discussion topics	
National Gender	1. In this meeting I was able to request the need of evaluation of Sectoral	
Sector Working	achievements and challenges for enhanced delivery of gender sector working groups.	
Group-Meeting	2. I was able to ask for the sharing of best practices pertaining to gender among	
	stakeholders.	
	3. Harness potential networks for effective mobilization and utilization of resources	
Africa	Attended 6 meetings on which the engagements and my contributions were not limited	
Industrialization Day	to; 1. programme of events 2. Invitation list for the guest. 3. Making of subcommittees	
Celebration Meetings	evaluation reports	
Substitutes(Regulation	I deeply looked at the Proposal for the amendments to the breast milk	
and Control Act 2012)	substitutes(Regulations and Control Act 2012) Regulations 2019 so as to help in	
Regulation 2019	regulating the manufacturers of such products	
SEZA Instruments	While attending a whole week seminar with Special Economic Zones; in the regulations I	
Retreat-SEZ	checked and contributed fully on: Regulations: 1.Supplementary Regulations	
Regulations	Arrangement of Regulations adjustments, 2. Amendment of the SEZA Act, 3. Review of	
	the Draft Regulations and adjustments. I therefore, majorly contributed in this tools	
Wage Bill Conference	Through written notes I was able to contribute my views to achieve a Fiscally	
	Sustainable Public Wage Bill in National Conference on Transforming Kenya's Economy.	
	Asking that we can make the country a 24 hour economy so as to generate wealth	
Awareness campaigns	After attending HIV & AIDS, Drugs and Substance Abuse meeting, I took packets of	
	condoms to the washrooms and after regular observations I believe that I saved lives.	
Status of Women in	In this meeting I offered my views that was promised to be incorporated 1. Business	
Manufacturing	case for Gender, Diversity, and Inclusion. 2. Mainstreaming Gender and Inclusion.	
European Business	I was the able to help in my capacity European Business Council while Looking	
Council	forward to get aid in facilitation at all Government institutions so as to enter Business in	
	Kenya	
Meeting with Ministry	I was among the officer from my state department who contributed to the proper	
of Foreign Affairs	facilitation for the Business forum during the official visit to Kenya by the Crown	
	Prince and Crown Princess of the Kingdom of Norway in the preparation meetings.	
Global Institute of	Contributed in the meetings Consultative meeting between the State Department and	
Management	Global Institute of Management on Local Content Mechanism Project	
Forum with KNBS	I managed to Review the National Strategy for Development of Statistics and	
	Development of the Gender Statistics Sector Plan. I contributed a lot in the final draft.	

Dinocci Industries, Boston US Data Analyst-Freelancer

April, 2018-May, 2019

Achievements/Accomplishments

- ➤ I was able to **do best research about solar energy** distribution over Massachusetts.
- Analyzing the available incentives for given address so as to calculate the available rebates for the particular given values.
- ➤ I have **excellently been performing Monitoring and Evaluation** on behave of Holly Towing company a department of the Dinocci Industries. My performance is online monitoring to meet the requirements of the contract with the AAA Northeast Roadside Assistance.
- Advising the stakeholders on the moves to make based on all the calculations and analysis.
- ➤ I have managed to aid the company grow from zero and still do progress. Aiming to put the company on a map and to be eventually a big play in the American economy.
- Created excel programmed template that calculates the rebates and all the incentives the government is offering for the given block address.
- ➤ Counter checking the forms to ensure all the standards are met before submission to the Department of Energy Resources Massachusetts federal government.
- ➤ I have successfully worked closely with other employees to make sure the company's project meet the standard and targets this is a great achievement to me since the interaction with individuals from different races and spheres over the world makes me learn many thigs from them.
- ➤ Holding meetings regularly with stakeholders and colleague employees to make sure we maintain course of achieving the set targets through regular briefings.
- ➤ 100% Creation of Excel Dashboards and programs that has been able to automate the calculations of data analysis according to SMART Solar Program Guidelines.

■ +254703475446 ■ leekiplimoarusei@gmail.com ■ www.linkedin.com/in/lee-arusei-b09033a0/

Aruli Data Center

MD June, 2016 -

Achievements/Accomplishments

Aruli Data Center is a system I have created and through which I execute all the tasks related to online work. Together with my team (though on & off) have been able to record a commendable progress as far as spheres pertaining to software uses is concerned. Working for my company as part time has never impacted negatively in anyway my service delivery to my employers. This is an angle to view all the opportunities that are deemed impossible but we deliver. For instance learning to from 0 knowledge to a level of an expert in the readily available computer programs.

Regular Tasks:

- Financial Analysis-Analyzed and interpreted large amounts of data to identify trends, gaps, inconsistencies and provide support to all end users and staff, prepared presentation within short stipulated time frame.
- > Strong and relevant experience creating effective **Tableau visualization** solutions that address financial and human resource related questions and for proper management of such departments.
- Extracted data, blended data, join data, and published data to Tableau server to help increase performance
- ➤ Writing of mathematics/statistical coursework proposals for different Universities.
- ➤ Perform audit on data and resolve business related issues purely customer base.
- > Supervise all client issues and coordinate with managers and supervisors and facilitate in deliverables.
- Monitor and organize all client invoices and perform all timely assessment for all payment issues.
- ➤ Good knowledge in Creating, Configuring, Deploying and Fine-tuning MS SQL Server Integration Service (SSIS) packages.
- > Supervise process management tools and ensure compliance to all cycle guidelines.
- Produce data for assigned clients and prepare information for client presentation.
- Create new processes for <u>data extraction</u> and <u>suggest automation tools for day-to-day analyses</u>.
- ➤ Proficient in using **T-SQL** for developing complex **Stored Procedures**, Effective Triggers, Tables, Views, User defined Functions, Relational Database Models and Data Integrity, **SQL** Joins, Indexing and **Ouerv** Writing.
- Analyzed and interpreted large amounts of data to <u>identify trends</u>, gaps, and inconsistencies.
- Random article writing based on the client's discretion.
- Attend occasional late-night and early-morning meetings with colleagues around the world.
- ➤ Reviewed basic **SQL** queries and edited inner, left, and right joins in Tableau Desktop by connecting live/dynamic and static datasets.
- > .Creation of Survey, data preparation and data analysis using SPSS, EXCEL and R
- > Coordinate and plan the Data Governance Sessions, meetings committees and councils.
- ➤ Created Bar Charts which is complied with data sets and added trend lines and forecasting on future usage of the Mobile App. Further produced Crosstabs to display underlying data based on various graphs and charts created for further data analysis.
- > Entered, Interpreted and analyzed data with use of software such as SQL and Tableau
- ArchiCAD15, AutoCAD, Corel Draw, all creations appreciating the tools that make work easier.

+254703475446 | leekiplimoarusei@gmail.com | www.linkedin.com/in/lee-arusei-b09033a0/

Kenya Pipeline Company Intern Benefits Officer

May 2016-Dec 2016

Achievements/Accomplishments

- ❖ I successful performed benefits calculation of several members who exited the Kenya Pipeline Company Retirement Benefits Scheme in accordance to the Trust Deeds and Rules. I achieved this at ease using programmed excel templates I created for different exit categories whether through deferment, early retirement or normal retirement and while using FundMaster software I followed the due diligence procedure successfully.
- ❖ Data entry while updating member's details both in the hard copy file systems and in softcopy into the Benefits department system. **I created the best entry list**
- ❖ Performing administrative duties excellently and successfully in absentia of the Admin Officer's Supervision Including preparing of attachment folder's for new interns and guiding through the general functions of the Scheme.
- ❖ Maintenances of records of all the daily activities done by the scheme revolving around service providers including communications and files keeping.
- Communicating with members on various stages involved right from the requirements to the final stages of payments of their pensions benefits: Involving both the Defined Benefits Scheme and Defined Contributions Schemes run by the Kenya Pipeline Retirement Benefits Scheme.
- Performed other duties assigned to me successfully involving dispatching letters and submission of payment vouchers and banker's checks to the rightful destinations,
- Involves risk management such as coming up with small analysis templates for use in investment strategy
- In accounting department I accomplished tasks including handling petty cash, debit and credit accounts reconciliation, financial analysis, and accrual of benefits.
- Prepared Payment vouchers and submitted for processing of payments for the various services offered by service providers and other stakeholders

REFEREES

1	2	3
Ms. Patricia Aruwa	Dr. Frankline K. Tireito	Rev. Dr. Fr. Thomas Kigen
Deputy Director Industries State Department for Industrialisation	Head of Mathematics Department Masinde Muliro University	Catholic Priest
Tel: +254728 320 460 Email: achiengaruwa@gmail.com	Tel: +254 720 515 162 Email: ftireito@mmust.ac.ke	Tel: +254722 625 532 Email:kigenthomas@yahoo.com